Why do artists use purple when coloring
something yellow? This is part of what
we call color theory. When you look at
the color wheel, purple and yellow are
complementary colors. This is because
they're across from each other and have
high contrast. But it also means that
when used together, they can mute the
other color and become a darker shade.
For this banana, instead of using black,
which can appear flat or overpowering,
we can use purple as part of the shadow.
On the other hand, just using a dark
yellow could be more vibrant, but it
wouldn't have as much dimension. The
same can be applied to the stem. Instead
of just using green, you can use other
colors like blue, which is its analogous
color, meaning the one next to it on the
color wheel. Because it appears more
similar, yet can still create a darker
shade when layered. This applies to all
mediums, but with acrylic markers, you
have to blend them fast since they dry
quickly. It also means it's easier to
correct if you accidentally color too
much or you want to add even more
darkness. And while this takes more time
because it's more colors and more
layers, you can clearly see the
difference color theory creates.